Imagine 2 machines.
They both output messages from
an alphabet of A, B, C, or D.
Machine 1 generates
each symbol randomly.
They all occur 25% of the time.
Machine 2 generates
symbols according
to the following probabilities.
Now, which machine is
producing more information?
Claude Shannon cleverly
rephrased the question.
If you had to predict the
next symbol from each machine,
what is the minimum number
of yes or no questions
you would expect to ask?
Let's look at Machine 1.
The most efficient way is
to pose a question which
divides the
possibilities in half.
For example, our
first question, we
could ask if it is any
2 symbols-- such as,
is it A or B?
Since there is a
50% chance of A or B
and a 50% chance of C or D.
After getting the answer,
we can eliminate half
of the possibilities.
And we will be left with 2
symbols, both equally likely.
So we simply pick
one-- such as, is it A?
And after this
second question, we
will have correctly
identified the symbol.
So we can say the
uncertainty of Machine 1
is 2 questions per symbol.
Now, what about Machine 2?
As with Machine 1, we
could ask two questions
to determine the next symbol.
However, this time the
probability of each symbol
is different.
So we can ask our
questions differently.
Here A has a 50%
chance of occurring,
and all other
letters add to 50%.
So we could start
by asking-- Is it A?
If it is A, we are done.
Only one question in this case.
Otherwise, we are left with 2
equal outcomes-- D or B and C.
So we could ask-- is it D?
If yes, we are done
with 2 questions.
Otherwise, we have to
ask a third question
to identify which of the
last 2 symbols it is.
On average, how many
questions do you
expect to ask to determine
a symbol from Machine 2?
And this can be explained
nicely with an analogy.
Let's assume instead we want to
build Machine 1 and Machine 2.
And we can generate symbols
by bouncing a disk off a peg
into 1 of 2 equally
likely directions.
Based on which way it falls,
we can generate a symbol.
So with Machine
1, we need to add
a second level or
a second bounce
so that we have 2
bounces, which lead
to 4 equally likely outcomes.
And based on where the disk
lands, we output A, B, C, or D.
Now, Machine 2.
In this case, the
first bounce leads
to either an A-- which occurs
50% of the time-- or else
we lead to a second bounce,
which then can either output
at D-- which occurs 25%
of the time-- or else
it leads to a third bounce,
which then leads to either B
or C-- 12.5% of the time.
So now we just take
a weighted average
as follows-- the expected
number of bounces
is the probability
of symbol A times 1
bounce plus the probability
of B times 3 bounces
plus the probability
of C times 3 bounces
of D times 2 bounces.
And this works out
to 1.75 bounces.
Now, notice the
connection between yes
or no questions
and fair bounces.
The expected number
of questions is
equal to the expected
number of bounces.
So Machine 1 requires 2
bounces to generate a symbol
while guessing an unknown
symbol requires 2 questions.
Machine 2 requires 1.75 bounces.
We need to ask 1.75
questions on average.
Meaning, if we need to guess
100 symbols from both machines,
we can expect to ask 200
questions for Machine 1
and 175 questions for Machine 2.
So this means that Machine 2
is producing less information
because there is
less uncertainty
or surprise about its output.
And that's it.
Claude Shannon calls this
measure of average uncertainty
"entropy," and he uses a
letter H to represent it.
And the unit of
entropy Shannon chooses
is based on the uncertainty
of a fair coin flip,
and he calls this
"the bit," which
is equivalent to a fair bounce.
And we can arrive at the
same result using our bounce
analogy.
Entropy, or H, is the
summation for each symbol
of the probability
of that symbol
times the number of bounces.
Now, the difference
is-- how do we
express number of bounces
in a more general way?
And as we've seen,
number of bounces
depends how far down
the tree we are.
And we can simplify
this by saying
that the number of bounces
equals the logarithm base 2
of the number of
outcomes at that level.
And the number of
outcomes at a level
is also based on the
probability, where
the number of
outcomes at a level
equals 1 divided by the
probability of that outcome.
Number of bounces actually
equals the logarithm base 2
of 1 over the probability
of that symbol, which
gives us our final equation.
Entropy, or H, is the
summation for each symbol
of the probability of that
symbol times the logarithm base
2 of 1 over the
probability of that symbol.
And Shannon writes this
slightly different,
which just inverts
the expression
inside the logarithm, which
causes us to add a negative,
though both formulas
give the same results.
So let's summarize.
Entropy is maximum when all
outcomes are equally likely.
Any time you move away from
equally likely outcomes
or introduce predictability,
the entropy must go down.
Now, the fundamental idea
is that if the entropy
of an information
source drops, that
means we can ask fewer
questions to guess the outcome.
And thanks to Shannon, the bit--
which is the unit of entropy--
is adopted as our
quantitative measure
of information or
measure of surprise.